Guide to the Sean Prendiville Collection AIA.005
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Sean Prendiville Collection
Bulk, 1920-1997
1818-1997 (bulk 1920-1997)
AIA.005
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.75 linear feet (6 boxes)
The Sean Prendiville collection contains a variety of material on the Irish American experience in Northern California as well as across the United States. The collection consists of personal correspondence and documentation in response to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests Prendiville made to the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) regarding several Irish American organizations and individuals suspected of Irish Republican activity circa 1920 through 1979. The requests were made between 1986 and 1994. Also included are original letters written by a Fenian prisoner in Western Australia in 1870 as well as newspaper accounts from that time. Ephemera both print and three dimensional round out the collection including bumper stickers supporting Irish Prisoners and the Republican movement, fliers and broadsides and a significant button collection.
Prendiville, Sean.
Provenance
Sean Prendiville donated the documents to the Archives of Irish America at the Tamiment Library, NYU in June 1997. The series of personal correspondence came to the Archives along with the Patrick Daughton Papers, AIA 055 in 2009.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sean Prendiville is a first generation Irish American, born and raised in San Francisco, California. His father emigrated from County Kerry, his mother from County Roscommon. In Ireland, members of the Prendiville family were active Republicans during the country’s fight for independence from Great Britain (1919-1921) and subsequent civil war (1922-1923). Two of Sean Prendiville’s grand-uncles were in the Irish Republican Army (IRA): one was killed in a raid on a Royal Irish Constabulary (police) station in Castleisland, County Kerry; the other continued to fight with the IRA until he was wounded and captured during the civil war. Their nephew in San Francisco regularly took young Sean Prendiville to buy the Sinn Fein newspaper The United Irishman at the Golden Gate News Agency on Third Street.
When conflict broke out in Northern Ireland in 1968, following attacks on Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association marches, Sean Prendiville joined some of the Irish support groups that were established in San Francisco. Later, after the Republican movement split, he joined the Irish Republican Clubs, supporters of the Official Irish Republican movement, because their politics seemed more in line with the anti-Vietnam war movement that he was also participating in at the time. While a member of the Irish Republican Clubs, Prendiville met some older activists who had participated in the Irish Republican Congress Clubs of the 1930s, especially Vernon Healey in San Francisco and Gerald O'Reilly in New York. He became aware of a current in Irish-American and Irish Republican history that had been passed over - the links between left-wing Irish organizations and American progressives – sparking a research interest that eventually led to the assembly of this collection between 1986 and 1994
Scope and Content Note
The Sean Prendiville Collection is divided into five series. Series I. Correspondence consists of personal correspondence between Prendiville and others. Of interest are two folders of correspondence between Prendiville and Gerald O'Reilly, prominent in the New York City Transit Workers Union and contemporary of Mike Quill. Included in their correspondence is material related to Frank Ryan and Fr. Michael Flanagan. Series II. Subject Files contains original letters and clippings related to the escape and rescue of Fenian prisoners held in Western Australia by American whaling ship the Catalpa. The series also includes literature from The Workers Party, including a manifesto, newsletters, pamphlets, and the Students Workers Party Bulletin.
Series II. Freedom of Information Act Requests comprised the bulk of the collection and consists of administrative papers, forms and documents relating to the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests Prendiville made from 1986 to 1994. Also included are his appeals for records the FBI chose to withhold. The files contain photocopies of memoranda, letters and reports generated by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) in their surveillance of Irish Republican activities in the United States between 1930 and 1979. Newspaper and magazine articles collected by the FBI, as well as copies of brochures and other literature distributed by Irish American organizations that the FBI was investigating are also included. Much of the material is heavily redacted.
The Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) dates from 1966 and generally provides that any person has the right to request access to federal agency records or information. All agencies of the Executive Branch of the United States Government are required to disclose records upon receiving a written request for them, except for those records (or portions of them) that are protected from disclosure by existing exemptions and exclusions of the FOIA. Prendiville requested files from the FBI and other agencies that might illuminate activities of certain Irish Republican organizations and individuals as covered by agency surveillance. He started a years-long process of making FOIA requests, receiving files with a huge number of excisions, appealing the excisions and sometimes appealing a second time. On rare occasions the appeals were so extensive that the FBI agreed with his objections. Letters that describe the scope of the FBI material about a specific Irish organization or individual have been copied and placed at the front of the first folder of each organization’s files.
The files provide a unique insight into the breadth of Irish Republican activity in the United States during the decades spanning the middle of the twentieth century. Many of the files contain collections of clippings from Irish publications, especially newspapers produced by support groups, that no longer exist and for which there may be no other surviving copies. They are also a useful cross-reference for the whereabouts of speakers on specific dates. Some of the files are notable for having either reports from very good internal FBI assets or reports from other groups. For example, the informer in the Irish American Labor League provides very detailed information about the state of the organization (as well as mention of some discussion of killing James Larkin). Files on the IRA include a very detailed assessment made during World War II by the Office of Strategic Services (predecessor of the Central Intelligence Agency). Some evidence points to mutual awareness of undercover activities: a series of internal Clan na Gael newsletters includes an Easter program that contains a satirical song about FBI surveillance. The copy sent to FBI headquarters has the song highlighted, presumably by the agent who received it; thus the Clan na Gael knew it was being watched and the FBI knew that the Clan knew it was being watched.
Files are arranged according to the FBI’s original identification and sequence numbers. The FBI assigned each organization a sequence number. For example, the Irish Republican Clubs are identified by the number 97-5329. Each specific document relating to that organization was then numbered sequentially; for example, 97-5329-25 identifies the twenty-fifth document in approximately chronological order. The FBI files also contain records that were filed under more than one organization; when cross-referenced like this, the documents do not have a sequence number. The order in which documents were supplied by the FBI has been maintained except when unknown; then they are filed chronologically. Following is a brief overview and background of the series’ contents.
Clan na Gael was founded in New York City in 1867 as a secret revolutionary society with Fenian connections. Among its many activities, it was instrumental in funding and otherwise supporting the Easter 1916 Rebellion in Dublin, Ireland. Its subsequent history in the twentieth century is primarily as an Irish American membership organization devoted to the Irish Republican cause, headquartered in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania but with several branches in other states including New York. Some documents in this series deal with Clan na Gael’s involvement in picketing British-sponsored events and illustrate the FBI’s concern about whether to require the Clan to comply with the U.S. Foreign Agents Registration Act.
James Connolly Clubs were named in honor of the Irish political activist James Connolly (1868-1916) and attracted members interested in the labor movement. They were organized and run by James Larkin (1876-1947), founder of the Irish Transport and General Workers Union who immigrated to the United States in 1914. This series contains one document relating specifically to this organization and parts of sixteen cross-references from other FBI files, including several duplicate pages supplied by the FBI.
James Gralton, a native of Drumsna, County Leitrim, was deported from Ireland for allegedly disseminating Communist ideas during the 1930s. The material in this series provides some details about Gralton’s passports and a few biographical details. One note states that Gralton had a record in the New York Police Department Bomb Squad’s “Radical and Anarchists” file. References to Gralton can also be found in files on the Irish American Labor League.
The Irish American Labor League, an offshoot of the James Connolly Clubs, was devoted to the interests of workers in both Ireland and America. The FBI seems to have been interested in this organization for its connections to the Communist Party in America. This series contains reports of Irish American Labor League meetings, as well as summaries of its organizational activities and its Communist ties, copies of brochures or brochure text with manifestos, and event announcements. All personal names were excised by the FBI from the copies provided to Sean Prendiville. Some reports reference the James Connolly Clubs and James Larkin. [Note: two numbering systems were used to organize this material: documents numbering 127-200 and pages numbering 14169-14333.]
Irish Republican Army (IRA) files contain reports, correspondence, and newspaper clippings from 1939-1975, generated by the FBI during its investigation into the American activities of the Irish Republican Army.
Irish Republican Clubs (IRC) were formed in 1971 by Irish Americans interested in the 32 county conception of Ireland and the achievement of full independence from Great Britain. The FBI seems to have had two principal concerns with the IRC: whether to require the clubs to comply with the U.S. Foreign Agents Registration Act, and whether the clubs were involved with raising funds for the Irish Republican Army and Sinn Fein. This files consist of FBI memoranda, particularly between local offices and Bureau headquarters in Washington, D.C., and also clippings from such publications as The Irish Echo, The Irish American Review, and The Advocate. Lengthy reports about the Irish Republican Clubs are also included.
National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) material is similar in format to that of National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ), a group it appears to have succeeded. In handouts and brochures the organization claimed to be “the U.S. agent” of the Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association; therefore the FBI was concerned about compliance with the U.S. Foreign Agents Registration Act. FBI memoranda and reports, text or copies of NAIF handouts and brochures advertising such demonstrations as that against the British Overseas Airline Corporation or the Office of the British Consulate General are included, as well as clippings from such publications as The Irish Echo, The Advocate, and The Daily Worker. Notable material includes FBI memoranda concerning possible demonstrations against First Lady Pat Nixon when she received an award from the American Irish Historical Society in the 1970s. Also of interest is correspondence (1975-1979) relating to an FOIA request made by Tom Naughton, NAIF’s Regional Coordinator.
The FBI appears to have believed the National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) was an agent of the Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association and possibly the Political Prisoners Defense Fund; therefore it sought records from the organization to determine if it was required to register under the U.S. Foreign Agents Registration Act. Material of note includes information on the organization’s connection with the Black Panthers and Northern Irish civil rights leader Bernadette Devlin, as well as information on the Artists’ Committee for Irish Freedom, the Irish Republican Movement, and the Irish Republican Clubs. The NAIJ declared itself defunct in February 1971. Material in the files indicates that the organization may have suffered from internal disagreements and reconstituted itself as the National Association for Irish Freedom.
The Citizens for Irish Justice (CIJ) was formed to support the Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association. It later split into three local affiliates of national organizations: Noraid, Irish Republican Clubs (IRC) and National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) and then later two additional groups: American Action Association and Irish Aid Committee. The CIJ button design was also adopted by the IRC. The evolution of the Official Sinn Fein to Sinn Fein the Workers Party to the Workers Park can also be traced through these buttons.
Series IV. Printed Ephemera and Series V. Nonprint includes Sean Prendiville's Button Collection, an assortment of political buttons from Irish organizations in the United States and Ireland. Prendiville has detailed notes for each group of buttons and these are included with the collection. The button collection includes items from Irish Republican Clubs, Irish Northern Aid, Citizens for Irish Justice, National Association for Irish Freedom, and other political and activist groups. Along with this collection is a complimentary set of bumper stickers and sashes or flags as well as 19th and 20th century fliers and broadsides.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into five series. Series are arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.
Series I. Correspondence, 1902-1997
Series II. Subject Files, 1864-1988
Series III. Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Requests and Correspondence, 1920-1979
Series IV. Printed Ephemera, 1818-1924
Series V. Nonprint, 1980-1995
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Harrison Papers AIA 009
Irish Republicanism Collection AIA 022
Patrick Daugton Collection AIA 055
Clan-na-Gael.; Gralton, Jimmy, 1886-1945; Irish American Labor League.; Irish Republican Army.; Irish Republican Brotherhood Veterans Association.; Irish Republican Clubs.; James Connolly Clubs.; McAliskey, Bernadette Devlin, 1947-; National Association for Irish Freedom (U.S.).; National Association for Irish Justice.; O'Reilly, Gerald, 1903-1990.; United Irish Republicans.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Women's Irish Educational League.; Articles.; Bumper stickers.; Buttons (information artifacts).; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Freedom of information |x Government policy |z United States.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Political activities.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.; New York (N.Y.); Philadelphia (Pa.).; Prisoners' writings, Irish.; Reports.; San Francisco (Calif.)
- Series I. Correspondence, 1902-1997
  - Cork Workers Club, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curtis, Liz (author), 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General; mostly Celtic Network I, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General; mostly Celtic Network II, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3A)
  - Irish American Voice (Entertprise, AL), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - O'Reilly, Gerald (Local 100, TWU, NYC) I, 1902-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - O'Reilly, Gerald (Local 100, TWU, NYC) II, 1902-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Research and Correspondence (includes two unidentified photographs), 1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Irish American Unity Conference: Membership papers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1864-1988
  - Catalpa: article in The Western Austrlian Times, Apr 21, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Catalpa: correspondence, newspaper accounts (very rare) Note: Most of the Catalpa-related material appears to be correspondence written to or from John B. Walsh, a Fenian who was transported to Australia after the Fenian Rising was broken up. Walsh was released after one of the round of amnesties, either 1869 or 1871, and settled in San Francisco. Transcriptions are included for some of the letters., 1864-1895 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Irish Republican Prisoners and Dependents Fund: Biographies of speakers and others, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Workers Party (Belfast): Manifesto, Newsletters, Pamphlets, Students Workers Party Bulletin, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series III: Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Requests and Correspondence, 1920-1992
  - Correspondence re: FOIA requests, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Government Materials - non-FBI, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clan na Gael c. 97-4883-1-97-4883-17, Mar 1964-Oct 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clan na Gael c. 97-4883-18-97-4883-40, Oct 1964-Sep 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gralton, James 65-35485-1;65-35485-5, Jun 1943-Oct 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Irish American Labor League c. 61-179-1-61-179-32, Oct 1921-Feb 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Irish American Labor League: Case 75, 75A, Doc. C. 127-152pages c. 14160-14213 (reports of agents, summary memos), Apr 1921-May 1921 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Irish American Labor League: Case 75, 75A, Doc. C. 153-201pages c. 14215 - 14295, May 1921-Jun 1921 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Irish American Labor League: Reports, memos related to Case 75pages c. 14298-14333 (illegible), Mar 1921, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Irish Radio Shows, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-1-61-7606-50, Sep 1939-Jul 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-51-61-7606-83, Jul 1940-Feb 1942 (bulk 1920-1997) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-84-61-7606-144, Jan 1942-Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-145-61-7606-209, Feb 1943-May 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-210-61-7606-260 I, May 1943-Oct 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-145-61-7606-260 II, May 1943-Oct 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-261-61-7606-342 I, Sep 1943-Dec 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-261-61-7606-342 II, Sep 1943-Dec 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-343-61-7606-393, Feb 1945-May 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-394-61-7606-451, Sep 1951-Oct 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-452-61-7606-501, Oct 1957-Nov 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-502-61-7606- c. 520s(some documents not numbered, cross-referenced), Nov 1963-Nov 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-?-61-7606-575(Some documents not completely numbered), Dec 1969-Oct 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-576-61-7606-653, Oct 1972-Feb 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-654-61-7606-721, Feb 1974-Feb 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-722-61-7606-831 I, Feb 1975-May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-722-61-7606-831 II, Feb 1975-May 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-A: news clippings, wire services - U.S, Ireland, U.K. events, 1939-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Irish Republican Brotherhood Veterans Association (FOIA #270, 640), 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-1-97-5329-16, Mar 1971-Sep 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-17-97-5329-31, Sep 1971-Jun 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-32-97-5329-52, Feb 1972-Nov 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-53-97-5329-81 I, Nov 1972-Jun 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-53-97-5329-81 II, Nov 1972-Jun 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-82-97-5329-112, Jul 1975-Aug 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Irish Workers Clubs, 1940-1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - James Connolly Clubs 62-17493-0, 1920-1924, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - James Gralton Defense Committee 9 FOIA #270, 234), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - James Larkin Defense Committee ( FOIA #270, 233), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-1 (Numbers not visible), Apr 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-2-1053212344-19 I, Jun 1971-Nov 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-2-1053212344-19 II, Jun 1971-Nov 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-21-105-212344-46 ( 20, 28 missing) I, Nov 1971-Jan 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-21-105-212344-46 ( 20, 28 missing) II, Nov 1971-Jan 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-47-105-212344-64 ( missing # 52 encl.), Jan 1973-Apr 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275 -xl- 97-5275-9, Aug 1969-Dec 1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-10-97-5275-25, Dec 1969-Mar 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-28-97-5275-35, Mar 1970-Jun 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-36-97-5275-59 I, Jul 1970-Nov 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-36-97-5275-59 II, Jul 197-Nov 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-60-97-5275-88, Nov 1970-Apr 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - United Irish Republicans (FOIA #297, 643), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women's Irish Educational League (FOAI #297, 646; Appeal #89-1-11), 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reference: Index to organization of material (SP), 1986-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Printed Ephemera, 1818-1924
  - Bond Certificates - Republic of Ireland - flier and postcard, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fliers and Broadsides: includes: "The truth about the Clan na Gael;" "The Irish World's Indictment of James G. Blaine;" "Brother Jonathan to the A.P.A.", 1818-1920, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publication: Brennan's: A weekly journal of advocating justice, equality and the preservation of American indenpenndence. Vol. 1, no. 1. (Chicago), Aug 16, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series V. Nonprint, 1980-1995
  - Button Collection, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Bumper stickers and penants, circa 1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Paperweight: James Connolly (sold by Anne Devlin IRC; from Gardiner Place, Dublin (Sinn Fein), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Silk handerchief/scarf "Remember '98" with images of: Robert Emmet, Wolfe Tone, Henry Joy McCracken, Lord Ed. Fitzgerald, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)